Nearly everyone in the world is part of some community,
ينتمي معظم سكان العالم إلى مجتمعٍ من نوعٍ ما،
whether large or small.
سواءً كان كبيراً أم صغيراً.
And all of these communities have similar needs.
وتتشابه كل هذه المجتمعات باحتياجاتها.
They need light,
إذ تحتاج إلى الإنارة،
they need heat
والحرارة،
they need air-conditioning.
والتكييف.
People can't function very well when it's too hot or too cold.
لا يستطيع الناس العمل بكفاءة في جوّ شديد الحرارة أو البرودة.
They need food to be grown or provided, distributed and stored safely.
وهم بحاجةٍ إلى زراعة الغذاء أو الحصول عليه وتوزيعه وتخزينه بشكل آمن.
They need waste products to be collected, removed and processed.
كما يحتاج الناس إلى جمع النفايات وإزالتها ومعالجتها
People in the community need to be able to get from one place to another
وإلى الانتقال من مكانٍ لآخر
as quickly as possible.
بأسرع وقتٍ ممكن.
And a supply of energy is the basis for all of these activities.
وتزويد الطاقة هو أساس جميع هذه الأنشطة.
Energy in the form of electricity provides light and air-conditioning.
فالطاقة الكهربائية تزوّد الإنارة والتكييف،
Energy in the form of heat keeps us warm.
والطاقة الحرارية تؤمن لنا الدفء
And energy in chemical form provides fertilizer;
والطاقة الكيميائية هي مصدر السماد
it drives farm machinery and transportation energy.
وهي التي تقود الآلات الزراعية وطاقة النقل.
Now, I spent 10 years working at NASA.
لقد أمضيت عشر سنواتٍ أعمل في وكالة ناسا
In the beginning of my time there in 2000,
وفي بداية عملي هناك في عام 2000،
I was very interested in communities.
كنت شديد الاهتمام بالمجتمعات.
But this is the kind of community I was thinking of --
ولكنّ المجتمع الذي كنت أفكر فيه
a lunar community
هو مجتمع على القمر.
It had all of the same needs as a community on Earth would have,
لديه نفس الاحتياجات التي قد توجد في أي مجتمعٍ على الأرض،
but it had some very unique constraints.
لكن مع بعض القيود الفريدة.
And we had to think about how we would provide energy
وكان علينا أن نفكر بطريقة لتزويد الطاقة
for this very unique community.
لهذا المجتمع الفريد.
There’s no coal on the Moon.
حيث لايوجد فحم على القمر،
There's no petroleum.
ولا يوجد نفط،
There’s no natural gas.
ولا يوجد غاز طبيعي،
There's no atmosphere.
كما أنه لا يوجد غلاف جوي
There’s no wind, either.
أو رياح.
And solar power had a real problem:
وكانت توجد مشكلة حقيقية في الطاقة الشمسية،
the Moon orbits the Earth once a month.
إذ يدور القمر حول الأرض مرة واحدة كل شهر
For two weeks, the sun goes down,
وتختفي الشمس لمدة أسبوعين،
and your solar panels don't make any energy.
ولا تنتج اللوحات الشمسية أية طاقة
If you want to try to store enough energy in batteries for two weeks,
حتى لو أردنا تخزين طاقة تكفي لأسبوعين فى بطاريات،
it just simply isn't practical.
فهذا ببساطة ليس أمراً عملياً
So nuclear energy was really the only choice.
لذا، كانت الطاقة النووية هي الخيار الوحيد
Now, back in 2000, I didn't really know too much about nuclear power,
لم أكن أعرف الكثير عن الطاقة النووية في عام 2000
so I started trying to learn.
لذا بدأت المحاولة بالتعلم
Almost all of the nuclear power we use on Earth today uses water
تعتمد معظم الطاقة النووية المستخدمة حالياً في الأرض على الماء
as a basic coolant.
كمادة تبريد أساسية
This has some advantages, but it has a lot of disadvantages.
الأمر الذي يتمتع ببعض الإيجابيات، لكن مقابل العديد من السلبيات
If you want to generate electricity, you have to get the water a lot hotter
لتوليد الكهرباء، علينا جعل الماء أكثر سخونة
than you normally can.
مما نصل إليه عادةً
At normal pressures, water will boil at 100 degrees Celsius.
يغلي الماء عند 100 درجة مئوية تحت الضغط الطبيعي
This isn't nearly hot enough to generate electricity effectively.
لكن ذلك غير كافٍ نهائياً لتوليد الكهرباء بفعالية.
So water-cooled reactors have to run at much higher pressures
ولذلك يجب تشغيل المفاعلات المبردة بالماء عند ضغط أعلى بكثير
than atmospheric pressure.
من الضغط الجوي.
Some water-cooled reactors run at over 70 atmospheres of pressure,
تعمل بعض المفاعلات المبردة بالماء عند ضغط أكبر بـ70 مرة من الضغط الجوي
and others have to run at as much as 150 atmospheres of pressure.
ويحتاج بعضها الآخر لضغط يصل إلى 150 مرة أكثر من الضغط الجوي.
There's no getting around this;
هذا ما لا يمكن تجنبه
it's simply what you have to do if you want to generate electricity
لأنه ببساطة ما يجب فعله لتوليد الكهرباء
using a water-cooled reactor.
باستخدام مفاعلٍ مبرد بالماء.
This means you have to build a water-cooled reactor
هذا يعني أنه لابد من بناء مفاعل مبرد بالماء
as a pressure vessel,
كوعاء ضغط
with steel walls over 20 centimeters thick.
ذو جدران من الفولاذ وبسماكة أكثر من 20 سنتيمتر.
If that sounds heavy, that's because it is.
قد يبدو هذا ثقيلاً وهو كذلك بالفعل!
Things get a lot worse if you have an accident
وستصبح الأمور أسوأ بكثير عند وقوع حادث
where you lose pressure inside the reactor.
نفقد فيه الضغط داخل المفاعل.
If you have liquid water at 300 degrees Celsius
إذا كان هناك ماء سائل بدرجة 300 مئوية
and suddenly you depressurize it,
وقمنا فجأة بإزالة الضغط عن الماء،
it doesn't stay liquid for very long;
فإنه لن يبقى سائلاً لفترة طويلة
it flashes into steam.
بل سيتحول إلى بخار.
So water-cooled reactors are built inside of big, thick concrete buildings
لذلك يتم بناء المفاعلات المبردة بالماء داخل مبانٍ خرسانية ضخمة وسميكة
called containment buildings,
تسمى بنايات الاحتواء النووي،
which are meant to hold all of the steam that would come out of the reactor
وتعمل على حجز كل البخار الذي قد يتسرب من المفاعل
if you had an accident where you lost pressure.
في حال وقوع حادثٍ وفقدان الضغط.
Steam takes up about 1,000 times more volume than liquid water,
يأخذ البخار حيزاً أكبر من الماء السائل ب1000 مرة
so the containment building ends up being very large,
لذا تصبح بناية الاحتواء النووي كبيرةً جداً
relative to the size of the reactor.
مقارنة بحجم المفاعل.
Another bad thing happens if you lose pressure
ويمكن أن يقع أمر سيىء آخر إذا فقدنا الضغط
and your water flashes to steam.
وإذا تحول الماء إلى البخار.
If you don't get emergency coolant to the fuel in the reactor,
إذا لم تكن تملك مبرد الطوارئ للوقود في المفاعل
it can overheat and melt.
فقد ترتفع حرارته جداً وينصهر.
The reactors we have today use uranium oxide as a fuel.
تستخدم المفاعلات الحالية أكسيد اليورانيوم كوقود.
It's a ceramic material similar in performance
وهي مادة خزفية تشبه في أدائها
to the ceramics we use to make coffee cups or cookware
المواد الخزفية المستخدمة لصناعة أكواب القهوة وأدوات الطهي،
or the bricks we use to line fireplaces.
أو الطوب المستخدم في تغليف المواقد من الداخل.
They're chemically stable,
فهي متوازنة كيميائياً
but they're not very good at transferring heat.
لكنها غير جيدة لنقل الحرارة.
If you lose pressure, you lose your water,
إذا فقدنا الضغط، سنفقد الماء
and soon your fuel will melt down
وخلال وقت قصير سينصهر الوقود
and release the radioactive fission products within it.
ويطلق نواتج الإنشطار الإشعاعية داخله.
Making solid nuclear fuel is a complicated and expensive process.
تعتبر صناعة الوقود النووي الصلب عملية معقدة وصعبة،
And we extract less than one percent of the energy for the nuclear fuel
ونستخرج أقل من 1% من الطاقة اللازمة للوقود النووي
before it can no longer remain in the reactor.
قبل أن تتسرب من المفاعل.
Water-cooled reactors have another additional challenge:
تواجه المفاعلات المبردة بالماء تحدياً آخر
they need to be near large bodies of water,
إذ يجب أن تكون قريبة من تجمعات ماء كبيرة
where the steam they generate can be cooled and condensed.
حيث يمكن تبريد وتكثيف البخار الناتج عنها.
Otherwise, they can't generate electrical power.
وإلا فلن تستطيع توليد الطاقة الكهربائية.
Now, there's no lakes or rivers on the Moon,
كما لا توجد بحيرات أو أنهار على القمر،
so if all of this makes it sound like water-cooled reactors
وهذا ما يجعل من المفاعلات المبردة بالماء
aren't such a good fit for a lunar community,
فكرة غير مناسبة لمجتمع على القمر.
I would tend to agree with you.
وأنا أتفق مع هذا الرأي!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I had the good fortune to learn about a different form of nuclear power
حالفني الحظ وتعرفت على شكل آخر من الطاقة النووية
that doesn't have all these problems,
لا يعاني من هذه المشاكل
for a very simple reason:
لسبب بسيط جداً:
it's not based on water-cooling, and it doesn't use solid fuel.
فهو لا يعتمد على التبريد بالماء ولا يستخدم الوقود الصلب.
Surprisingly, it's based on salt.
والمدهش أنه يعتمد على الملح.
One day, I was at a friend's office at work,
كنت مرة في مكتب صديق في العمل
and I noticed this book on the shelf, "Fluid Fuel Reactors."
ولاحظت كتاباً على الرف بعنوان "مفاعلات الوقود السائل"
I was interested and asked him if I could borrow it.
أبديت اهتماماً وطلبت استعارة الكتاب.
Inside that book, I learned about research in the United States
وتعلمت منه عن الأبحاث في الولايات المتحدة
back in the 1950s,
خلال فترة الخمسينيات
into a kind of reactor that wasn't based on solid fuel
حول نوع من المفاعلات لا يعتمد على الوقود الصلب
or on water-cooling.
أو على التبريد بالماء.
It didn't have the problems of the water-cooled reactor,
ولا يعاني من مشاكل المفاعل المبرد بالماء
and the reason why was pretty neat.
والسبب في ذلك بسيط جداً.
It used a mixture of fluoride salts as a nuclear fuel,
وهو استخدامه لأملاح الفلوريد كوقود نووي
specifically, the fluorides of lithium, beryllium, uranium and thorium.
وخاصة فلوريد الليثيوم والبيريليوم واليورانيوم والثوريوم.
Fluoride salts are remarkably chemically stable.
وبشكل ملحوظ، فإن أملاح الفلوريد متوازنة كيمائياً،
They do not react with air and water.
إذ لا تتفاعل مع الهواء والماء.
You have to heat them up to about 400 degrees Celsius
ويجب أن ترفع درجة حرارتها ل400 درجة مئوية
to get them to melt.
حتى تنصهر.
But that's actually perfect for trying to generate power
ولكن هذا أمر مثالي من أجل محاولة توليد الطاقة
in a nuclear reactor.
في مفاعل نووي.
Here's the real magic:
وهنا يكمن السحر الحقيقي:
they don't have to operate at high pressure.
فهي ليست بحاجة لأن تعمل تحت ضغط مرتفع.
And that makes the biggest difference of all.
الأمر الذي يشكل الفرق الأكبر.
This means they don't have to be in heavy, thick steel pressure vessels,
هذا يعني أنها ليست بحاجة لتكون في أوعية ضغطٍ فولاذية سميكة وثقيلة
they don't have to use water for coolant
ولا يجب أن تستخدم الماء كمادة تبريد.
and there's nothing in the reactor
كما أنه لا يوجد في المفاعل شيء
that's going to make a big change in density, like water.
قد يغير الكثافة تغييراً كبيراً، كالماء.
So the containment building around the reactor
لذا فيمكن لبناية الاحتواء النووي حول المفاعل
can be much smaller and close-fitting.
أن تكون أصغر وأضيق بكثير.
Unlike the solid fuels that can melt down if you stop cooling them,
بعكس الوقود الصلب الذي يمكن أن ينصهر في حال توقف التبريد عنه،
these liquid fluoride fuels are already melted,
كما تكون أنواع وقود الفلوريد هذه منصهرة بالأساس
at a much, much lower temperature.
عند درجة حرارة أقل بكثير.
In normal operation, you have a little plug here
كما يوجد قابس صغير في العملية العادية
at the bottom of the reactor vessel.
في أسفل وعاء المفاعل.
This plug is made out of a piece of frozen salt
وهذا القابس مصنوع من قطعة ملحٍ مجمدة
that you've kept frozen by blowing cool gas
تم الحفاظ عليها جامدة عبر نفخ غاز بارد
over the outside of the pipe.
فوق الأنبوب الخارجي.
If there's an emergency and you lose all the power
عند حدوث أمر طارئ وفقدان كل الطاقة
to your nuclear power plant,
في محطة الطاقة النووية
the little blower stops blowing,
فسيتوقف المنفاخ الصغير عن النفخ
the frozen plug of salt melts,
وينصهر المقبس ذو الملح المجمد
and the liquid fluoride fuel inside the reactor
أما وقود الفلوريد السائل داخل المفاعل
drains out of the vessel, through the line
فيرشح خارج الوعاء عبر الخط
and into another vessel called a drain tank.
إلى وعاء آخر يدعى خزان التصريف.
Inside the drain tank, it's all configured to maximize the transfer of heat,
وتم تصميم الجزء الداخلي للخزان بحيث يرفع ناقلية الحرارة إلى أقصى حد
so as to keep the salt passively cooled
حتى يحافظ على الملح مبرداً بشكل سلبي
as its heat load drops over time.
حيث تنخفض حرارته مع الوقت.
In water-cooled reactors,
في المفاعلات المبردة بالماء،
you generally have to provide power to the plant
فيجب أن تتوفّر الطاقة لدى المحطة
to keep the water circulating and to prevent a meltdown,
لتحافظ على دوران الماء وتمنع الانصهار
as we saw in Japan.
كما رأينا في اليابان.
But in this reactor, if you lose the power to the reactor,
ولكن في هذه المفاعل، إذا فقدت الطاقة في المفاعل،
it shuts itself down all by itself, without human intervention,
فستنفصل تلقائياً دون تدخل الإنسان
and puts itself in a safe and controlled configuration.
وتدخل في وضع آمن ومضبوط.
Now, this was sounding pretty good to me,
بدا هذا الأمر جيداً جداً بالنسبة لي
and I was excited about the potential of using a liquid fluoride reactor
وكنت متحمساً حول إمكانية استخدام مفاعل الفلوريد
to power a lunar community.
لإمداد مجتمع القمر بالطاقة.
But then I learned about thorium, and the story got even better.
ولكني تعلمت عن الثوريوم وقتها وأصبحت الأمور أفضل.
Thorium is a naturally occurring nuclear fuel
الثوريوم هو وقود نووي موجود طبيعياً
that is four times more common in the Earth's crust than uranium.
وينتشر في قشرة الأرض أكثر من اليورانيوم بأربع مرّات.
It can be used in liquid fluoride thorium reactors
يمكن استخدامه في مفاعلات فلوريد الثوريوم السائل
to produce electrical energy, heat and other valuable products.
لإنتاج طاقة كهربائية وحرارة وغيرها من المنتجات القيّمة.
It's so energy-dense that you could hold a lifetime supply of thorium energy
وهو غني بالطاقة لدرجة أنه يمكنك الحصول على مخزون من طاقة الثوريوم مدى الحياة
in the palm of your hand.
في راحة يدك.
Thorium is also common on the Moon and easy to find.
والثوريوم منتشر وسهل الإيجاد على القمر.
Here's an actual map of where the lunar thorium is located.
هذه خريطة حقيقية لمواقع الثوريوم على القمر.
Thorium has an electromagnetic signature that makes it easy to find,
للثوريوم إشارة كهرومغنطيسية تجعل من السهل العثور عليه
even from a spacecraft.
حتى من سفينة فضائية.
With the energy generated from a liquid fluoride thorium reactor,
باستخدام الطاقة التي يولدها مفاعل فلوريد الثوريوم السائل،
we could recycle all of the air, water and waste products
يمكننا إعادة تدوير الهواء والماء والنفايات
within the lunar community.
في المجتمع على القمر.
In fact, doing so would be an absolute requirement for success.
في الواقع، يعتبر هذا متطلباً أساسياً للنجاح.
We could grow the crops needed to feed the members of the community
يمكن زراعة المحاصيل الضرورية لإطعام أفراد المجتمع
even during the two-week lunar night,
حتى خلال ليلة القمر ذات الأسبوعين
using light and power from the reactor.
باستخدام الضوء والطاقة من المفاعل.
It seemed like the liquid fluoride thorium reactor, or LFTR,
يبدو أن مفاعل فلوريد الثوريوم السائل أو LFTR
could be the power source that could make a self-sustainable lunar colony
يمكن أن يكون مصدر الطاقة التي ستجعل مستعمرة مستدامة ذاتياً على القمر
a reality.
أمراً واقعاً.
But I had a simple question:
ولكن يراودني سؤال بسيط:
If it was such a great thing for a community on the Moon,
إذا كانت فكرة مجتمع على القمر أمراً عظيماً
why not a community on the Earth, a community of the future,
فلم لا يكون مجتمع الأرض، مجتمع المستقبل
self-sustaining and energy-independent?
يتمتع باستدامة ذاتية واستقلالية في الطاقة؟
The same energy generation and recycling techniques
يمكن لتقنيات توليد الطاقة وإعادة التدوير نفسها
that could have a powerful impact on surviving on the Moon
التي قد تؤثر بقوة على استمرار الحياة على القمر
could also have a powerful impact on surviving on the Earth.
أن تؤثر بقوة على استمرار الحياة على الأرض.
Right now, we're burning fossil fuels
حالياً نحن نحرق الوقود الأحفوري
because they're easy to find and because we can.
لأنه من السهل العثور عليه، ولأننا نستطيع ذلك.
Unfortunately, they're making some parts of our planet look like the Moon.
لكنه مع الأسف يحوّل أجزاءً من كوكبنا إلى ما يشبه القمر.
Using fossil fuels entangles us in conflict
يضعنا استخدام الوقود الأحفوري في صراع
in unstable regions of the world
في مناطق غير مستقرة حول العالم،
and costs money and lives.
ويكلف المال والأرواح.
Things could be very different if we were using thorium.
وقد يتغير الوضع كثيراً إذا استخدمنا الثوريوم.
You see, in a LFTR, we could use thorium about 200 times more efficiently
نستطيع في هذا النوع من المفاعل استخدام الثوريوم بفاعلية أكثر ب200 مرة
than we're using uranium now.
مما نستخدم اليورانيوم الآن.
And because the LFTR is capable of almost completely releasing
وبما أنه قادر بشكل شبه كامل على تحرير
the energy in thorium,
الطاقة في الثوريوم
this reduces the waste generated over uranium by factors of hundreds,
فإنه يقلل الهدر الناتج عن اليورانيوم بمئات المرات،
and by factors of millions over fossil fuels.
والهدر الناتج عن الوقود الأحفوري بملايين المرات.
We're still going to need liquid fuels for vehicles and machinery,
سنبقى بحاجة للوقود السائل من أجل العربات والآلات،
but we could generate these liquid fuels from the carbon dioxide in the atmosphere
لكننا سنستطيع توليد هذا الوقود من ثنائي أكسيد الكربون في الجو
and from water, much like nature does.
ومن الماء، كما يتم توليده في الطبيعة.
We could generate hydrogen by splitting water
سنتمكن من توليد الهيدروجين عبر تفكيك الماء
and combining it with carbon harvested from CO2 in the atmosphere,
ودمجه مع الكربون الناتج من ثنائي أكسيد الكربون في الجو،
making fuels like methanol, ammonia, and dimethyl ether,
مما سيصنع وقوداً مثل الميثانول والنشادر وثنائي ميثيل الإيثر
which could be a direct replacement for diesel fuels.
والتي قد تكون بديلاً مباشراً لوقود الديزل.
Imagine carbon-neutral gasoline and diesel,
تخيلوا أنواع بنزين وديزل محايدةً للكربون
sustainable and self-produced.
ومستدامة وذاتية الإنتاج.
Do we have enough thorium?
هل نملك ما يكفي من الثوريوم؟
Yes, we do.
نعم.
In fact, in the United States, we have over 3,200 metric tons of thorium
في الواقع، يوجد في الولايات المتحدة أكثر من 3,200 طن متري من الثوريوم
that was stockpiled 50 years ago
الذي تم اختزانه منذ 50 سنة
and is currently buried in a shallow trench in Nevada.
وهو مدفون حاليًا في خندق ضحل في نيفادا.
This thorium, if used in LFTRs,
وإذا تم استخدام هذا الثوريوم في المفاعل،
could produce almost as much energy as the United States uses in three years.
فيمكنه أن ينتج طاقة تعادل ما تستخدمه الولايات المتحدة خلال ثلاث سنوات.
And thorium is not a rare substance, either.
كما أن الثوريوم ليس من المواد النادرة.
There are many sites like this one in Idaho,
وهنالك عدة مواقع كهذه في ولاية أيداهو،
where an area the size of a football field would produce enough thorium each year
حيث يمكن لمنطقة بمساحة ملعب كرة قدم أن تنتج في كل عام ما يكفي من الثوريوم
to power the entire world.
لتزويد كل العالم بالطاقة.
Using liquid fluoride thorium technology,
باستخدام تقنية فلوريد الثوريوم السائل
we could move away from expensive and difficult aspects
يمكننا الابتعاد عن المظاهر الصعبة والغالية
of current water-cooled, solid-fueled uranium nuclear power.
لطاقة نووية لليورانيوم، والتي تعمل بوقود صلب ومياه مبردة
We wouldn't need large, high-pressure nuclear reactors
لن نحتاج للمفاعلات النووية الضخمة ذات الضغط المرتفع،
and big containment buildings that they go in.
ولا لأبنية الاحتواء النووي التي تحويها.
We wouldn't need large, low-efficiency steam turbines.
ولن نحتاج للتوربينات البخارية الضخمة منخفضة الكفاءة.
We wouldn't need to have
ولن نضطر لامتلاك
as many long-distance power transmission infrastructure,
العديد من البنى التحتية البعيدة المدى والناقلة للطاقة.
because thorium is a very portable energy source
لأن الثوريوم يعتبر مصدر طاقة سهل التنقل
that can be located near to where it is needed.
ويمكن وضعه بالقرب من مكان استخدامه.
A liquid fluoride thorium reactor would be a compact facility,
يمكن أن يكون مفاعل فلوريد الثوريوم السائل وسيلة مدمجة
very energy-efficient and safe,
آمنة وعالية الكفاءة بالطاقة،
that would produce the energy we need day and night,
وتنتج الطاقة التي نحتاجها في الليل والنهار
and without respect to weather conditions.
وبدون التأثر بعوامل الطقس.
In 2007, we used five billion tons of coal,
في عام 2007، قمنا باستخدام 5 مليار طن من الفحم
31 billion barrels of oil
و31 مليار برميل من النفط
and five trillion cubic meters of natural gas,
و5 تريليون متر مكعب من الغاز الطبيعي
along with 65,000 tons of uranium
بالإضافة لـ65,000 طن من اليورانيوم
to produce the world's energy.
لإنتاج طاقة للعالم.
With thorium, we could do the same thing
مع الثوريوم، يمكننا القيام بنفس الشيء
with 7,000 tons of thorium that could be mined at a single site.
باستخدام 7000 طن من الثوريوم والتي يمكن استخراجها من موقع واحد.
If all this sounds interesting to you, I invite you to visit our website,
إذا كنتم مهتمين بهذا، أدعوكم لزيارة موقعنا الالكتروني
where a growing and enthusiastic online community of thorium advocates
حيث يقوم مجتمع الكتروني متنامي ومتحمس من مؤيدي الثوريوم
is working to tell the world about how we can realize a clean, safe
بالعمل على إخبار العالم عن إمكانية تحقيق مستقبل طاقة
and sustainable energy future,
نظيف وآمن ومستدام.
based on the energies of thorium.
بالاعتماد على طاقات الثوريوم.
Thank you very much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلاً. (تصفيق)